Hello friends, while getting a car or any other vehicle
insured, we definitely ask this question
that how much value is there in it for
our vehicle. Now friends,
in the language of insurance, that value word is
also called IDBI from Had and Should
Declared Value, that is,
how much has the insured declared for himself.
Now many questions related to this also arise in the mind that
how much will the TV cost of a new car, how much will it decrease every year, can
it be increased or when
God forbid, there is a loss in the total amount, then
how much value will we get in that case.
Now friends, the answer to all these questions will be
clear in all these graphics by the end of this video. Hello friends, my
name is Harvinder Singh and you are watching
DEC 16 Sanskar YouTube channel, this is the best
medium to understand insurance in very simple
language. So first of all, let us
know how the ID of a new vehicle
is decided. But friends, when you go to
buy a vehicle, then there
you get the ex-showroom price, after that a
tax is added to it, so the
ex-showroom price is
its five percent deduction.  It is charged in the form of Rs.
in the case of a new car.
So let us understand it as an example,
suppose the ex-showroom price of your new car
is Rs. 10 and five percent of it is Rs. 50,000,
then at the time of buying a new car, the
ID of your car will also be mentioned in your insurance policy,
that Rs. 10 lakh - Rs. 50,000 or Rs. 9.5 lakh will be
declared in it and if the
total of that car is Rs. 9.5 lakh, then the
liability of the insurance company to present this will also be Rs. 9.5 lakh.
Now many such cases also
come in which our army personnel, fauja
brothers, go to buy their car,
seriously, they definitely
get some rebate, so what will be the value of the car in that case,
see, the report they
get is traction, so the ex-
showroom price will be calculated for them also
and there will be no deduction in their ID, so
for them also
Rs. 9.5 lakh ID will also be mentioned
in their insurance policy, so according to this, the
decision is made to buy a new car. Now the second
question arises that it should be reduced every year.  How does it
happen, what is the criteria for how much it will reduce,
you cannot do this arbitrarily,
for this the previous FIR has been defined
which I will tell you also which
you can see on the screen right now, if
you buy a new vehicle, it is
not older than six months, it is a new vehicle or it has
not been older than 6 months, then there will be a
definition charge of 5%, as I
told you in the examples, if it is
between last month to one year old and if
you want to get insurance done, then
you will be charged 15% of the
ex-showroom amount, that is, 20%
for 1 to 2 years,
30% for 2 to 3 years, 40% for 3 to 4 years and
increasing like this, the
decoration between 4 to 5 years is cashless 50
%, that is, in the first 5 years your
vehicle price will be reduced to half as per the insurance ID slab,
after that its reduction will be very
slow, the decision after that
remains between the insurance company and you,
every insurance company decides this on
every model and on its own will  You
can give your ID as per the manufacturing for any option,
then you can also give your ID in another company, if you like the
value of your vehicle, you
can buy insurance policy from there, now
after this friends this question arises whether we
can increase or decrease it, see if you have
slapped a body for the first 5 years, you have to try to
decorate the value of your vehicle according to the slab, if
you reduce the value of your vehicle, which is the price of your vehicle, then the
value of the vehicle will also decrease, so there is
no benefit in it, if you fly it, if you
maintain it for profit intentions or
market value in tension, then that
is also not right because for this an IRDA has
defined a slab, then you should follow that only,
now suppose you have
increased the value of your
vehicle by a little according to a slab, then there is no problem at that time,
politicians also get it, but at the
time of plane, Vedavyas is done, the
insurance company will check that
who were the people in your previous pool C and what did
you do from this corner
If you have declared it as per IIT Roorkee and there is
10% depression then they will
select your claim, otherwise they will
give you claim only for this rally and that too. So there is
no benefit in increasing the value without any reason
because it is not at all the market
value. Now that could be the market value of
your medical, Rs 78 lakh and the
insurance that is being made at home, then
we have to focus only on the insurance value, that
how much it is according to that, so do not tamper with it, it is
okay if the negligible things go wrong,
suppose we have paid more
premium for the vehicle and then we take it away saying
that we have got it for free,
you will do this as per the rules,
we will have to face trouble in this without any reason, it is
possible that the decision may also come to our feet
but that trouble will remain only, its
rescue is not right that the
difference in value that you have made and the efforts that
you will have to make to get that item,
that visual ratio is not right, so
if
you put the value of your vehicle according to the rules, then your  It will be best for you.
Now friends, the final question
was asked, if the vehicle gets totaled then
how will its value be decided, friends,
for that also this idea will be defined according to the slab,
from the free explosions that will be asked from you and then
it will be seen how much the value of the vehicle is. At the
time of accident, our pole
cement cleared IDV is not always correct
because we have a slab, the
company gives some criteria
that it can be
applied between this much and this much, but we should
apply it only after quitting the previous polish,
because at the time of claim, the
company will make the last decision and will give
us the claim of the eligible amount, even after
declaring anything, then
that profit intention goes away that we
want to earn profit through yes and that is
against the rules of insurance, so friends,
now the essence of this entire video is that if you
apply the insurance value according to the defined slab, then it will be
best for you, neither less nor more than that
because clean we will get this much value.  It is going to happen
and many times it also happens that there is
profit intention that if I put a higher value then there will be a
total loss in the car and
I will earn a profit, then that is absolutely wrong, you
should not do this and in
such a way that you will only suffer losses, so avoid doing this and follow the rules and guidelines, so friends, I hope the entire concept would have been clear in tomorrow's episode of ID about a plate value and according to which you have to put the value of the car,
if you want to get such important information from me then do
not forget to subscribe to the channel and if you liked the video then do
like and share it, so friends,
through this channel our aim is that
you do not suffer any loss due to lack of awareness or
due to not knowing your rights,
whatever premium policy you
paste, then you should get its full coverage
and
you do not suffer any loss due to lack of any information, so friends,
see you next week with more good information, till then please
allow me, take
care of yourself, stay healthy and be happy,
thank you, do it, do it